Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Collection, The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley
BANC MSS 72/234 z Bancroft
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry prose Manuscripts
The Bancroft Library The Bancroft Library University of California, Berkeley Berkeley, California 94720-6000
This catalog was created from the original finding aid obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and finding aid are held in Rare Books and Special Collections, The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with repository.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection, working notes for Specimen Days, has been divided into three sections. The first contains all the prefatory notes and references to the writing, the content, and the title of the book (including some which may in fact describe other works); these are arranged by title or first line of manuscript not crossed out. The second contains notes for the various chapters of Specimen Days, arranged and published by title; if there is more than one fragmentary note for the chapter, they are arranged in order of their appearance in the chapter. The third contains all notes which could not be indentified as related to a particular chapter, and possibly not to Specimen Days itself; they have been arranged by title or first line. The Walt Whitman Collection holds two poetry manuscripts. This catalog includes item-level descriptions of only those items deemed poetry and prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- The Singer in the Prison The Singer in the Prison, ca. 1875; ucb.00001; xxx.00233; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 47)
  A corrected proof of the poem The Singer in the Prison, first published in the Saturday Evening Visitor ( 25 December 1869 ), reprinted in Passage to India ( 1871 ) and Leaves of Grass ( 1881–1882 and 1891–1892 ). Notes in pencil indicate Whitman was thinking of a potential connection with Parepa Rosa, a famous nineteenth-century opera singer. The verso contains prose notes about horses.
- Wood Odors Wood Odors Poem, ca. 1875; ucb.00002; xxx.00505; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 3)
  A draft of a poem unpublished in Whitman's lifetime entitled Wood Odors. The poem was apparently written as Whitman was making notes for his 1882-1883 book, Specimen Days & Collect. Specifically, the poem appears to respond to the visit he made to the Stafford farm in New Jersey in the mid-1870s. Some have argued that this draft is not a poem at all, but a list of phrases toward the composition of Specimen Days & Collect (see David Goodale, Wood Odors, Walt Whitman Review 8 [ March 1962 ], 17). Wood Odors was published first in Harper's Magazine 221 ( December 1960 ), 43.
- —and many an autumn sight [and many an autumn sight], 1876–1882; ucb.00037; xxx.00811; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Two scraps of paper pasted to a backing sheet to make one leaf. These scraps feature draft lines which appeared slightly revised in the 29 January 1881 issue of the The Critic as part of How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the section heading Autumn Scenes and Sights. Whitman continued to revise this piece of prose, eventually publishing it as Autumn Side-Bits, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
- As I loiter amid a scene [? to conclude 'Footsteps'], 1876–1882; ucb.00007; xxx.00812; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 12)
  A heavily revised prose fragment which features the heading, "? to conclude 'Footsteps.'" "Footsteps" was possibly a working title for Specimen Days & Collect. The final line of the prose fragment—"In serene hours, to the Soul, of a fine day or night, Nature seems to look even on the best Poetry and Art as something foreign, something almost impertinent"—appeared with some revisions in Final Confessions—Literary Tests, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). On the verso of this manuscript is a portion of a letter from J. S. Smith to Whitman, requesting the poet's autograph.
- A Bit of a Preface [A Bit of Preface], 1879; ucb.00008; xxx.00813; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 14)
  A prose note, headed "Preface—Paragraph" and dated "?Oct Sept '79," with "A Bit of Preface" scrawled in the upper-left-hand corner of the page. Though Whitman apparently intended these notes for a preface, portions of this manuscript were used in An Early Summer Reveille, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
- I have written these memoranda [I have jotted down these memoranda], 1876–1882; ucb.00013; xxx.00814; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 20)
  A short prose manuscript that reads like notes towards a preface. However, Whitman appears to have returned to this manuscript at a later date, revising some phrases and suggesting that this scrap is the "best foot note of all for first page." In fact, portions of this manuscript were used in Whitman's footnote to New Themes Entered Upon, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ).
- I just spin out my notes [I just spin out my notes], 1876–1882; ucb.00014; xxx.00812; xxx.00814; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Three scraps of paper, pasted together to make one leaf. Whitman used lines from this manuscript in separate sections of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). A large portion of this manuscript was revised and appeared under the heading, Final Confessions—Literary Tests. The line which reads, "I must take notes (The ruling passion strong in sickness and—But I must not say it yet)," appeared slightly revised in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic, under the title How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1.) before appearing in Specimen Days, as part of the section titled New Themes Entered Upon.
- Wherever I go, or winter or summer [Jan 12 1881], ucb.00026; xxx.00814; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Five scraps of paper containing prose notes. One scrap is dated January 12, 1881. On another scrap, "in preface? to my Notes" is written along the top of the page. Together these five scraps of paper comprise a nearly complete draft of New Themes Entered Upon, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). This piece of prose first appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic, under the title How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1) before it was published in Specimen Days and finally collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Some lines in this manuscript can also be found in [I just spin out my notes], another prose manuscript held in the Livezey collection.
- Gossip of Early Candle Light Gossip of Early Candlelight, 1880; ucb.00011; xxx.00836; prose poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Prose notes, titled "Gossip of Early Candlelight." Portions of this manuscript appeared in An Interregnum Paragraph, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). The second leaf contains draft lines for the poem, A Clear Midnight, see the description for ucb.00065 in this finding aid.
- Gossip of Early Candle Light [still call myself a Half-Paralytic], 1880; ucb.00065; xxx.00291; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Draft lines of the poem, A Clear Midnight, which appeared slightly revised in the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves of Grass. This manuscript also includes lines that were used in Specimen Days & Collect, see the description for ucb.00011 in this finding aid.
- Brook Babbling [Brook Babbling], 1876–1890; ucb.00029; xxx.00815; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Prose notes titled "Brook Babbling" with another possible title, "?Sounds," written in the upper-left-hand corner of the page. Portions of this manuscript appeared slightly revised in To the Spring and Brook, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Cedar-apples cedar-apples, 1878; ucb.00030; xxx.00816; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Draft notes of a short prose item, dated 25 April 1878. This prose piece appeared undated in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) titled, Cedar-Apples.
- The silent darting of many sand swallows [—the silent darting of many sand swallows], ca. 1876–1877; ucb.00032; xxx.00817; prose poetry 3 leaves handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Prose notes in which Whitman provides a detailed sensory description of a pastoral setting, possibly the "charmingly recluse and rural spot along Timber Creek" where Whitman spent restorative time in the mid- to late-1870s. Lines from this manuscript appeared in Sundown Perfume—Quail-Notes—The Hermit-Thrush, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), which was later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of the third leaf is a corrected proof of The Singer in the Prison, also described in this finding aid (see the entry for ucb.00001).
- Locusts and Katy-Dids [Then the reedy monotone], ca. 1876–1877; ucb.00033; xxx.00818; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Two scraps of paper featuring notes on the "reedy monotones of the locust." Whitman included some of these lines in Locusts and Katydids, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Locusts and Katydids was later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- The Lesson of a Tree The Lesson of a Tree, 1876–1877; ucb.00034; xxx.00819; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 50)
  A partial draft of The Lesson of a Tree, which was published as a section of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), and collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- One lesson from studying and affiliating a tree [One lesson from studying], 1876–1877; ucb.00035; xxx.00819; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 49)
  A draft fragment that Whitman used in slightly revised form in The Lesson of a Tree, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before including it in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- The ground in all directions is stretched [last of Sept. '76], 1876–1877; ucb.00036; xxx.00811; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 52)
  A draft paragraph describing Whitman's time at Timber Creek, where he spent some restorative time in the mid- to late-1870s. Much of this draft first appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic, as part of How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the section heading Autumn Scenes and Sights. This piece of prose was slightly revised and eventually published as Autumn Side-Bits, in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before appearing in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Sept. 20 '76 [Sept 20 '76], 1876; ucb.00038; xxx.00811; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 51)
  A draft fragment, portions of which Whitman first published in How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), The Critic 29 January 1881, under the heading Autumn Scenes and Sights. Whitman used this portion of prose nearly unchanged in Autumn Side-Bits, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Autumn Side-Bits was eventually collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Part of the sky [?Part of the Sky], 1876–1877; ucb.00039; xxx.00820; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 55)
  A heavily revised draft fragment of The Sky—Days and Nights—Happiness, a section of prose that appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and was later published in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). This manuscript includes Whitman's notes and thoughts on Byron, happiness, and the "German legend of the King's Bell." Whitman composed this draft on the verso of a letter sent from Richard J. Hinton, dated 12 December.
- Night of Oct. 11— [Night of Oct 11], 1876–1877; ucb.00040; xxx.00820; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 56)
  A small scrap of paper containing Whitman's notes on the night sky, "the heavens unusually transparent." Though Whitman dates this note "night of Oct 11," the description which appeared in The Sky—Days and Nights—Happiness, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) is dated "Night of Oct. 28." The Sky—Days and Nights—Happiness was later published in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Sky [Sky], 1878; ucb.00041; xxx.00820; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
  A partial draft of The Sky—Days and Nights—Happiness, initially dated Oct 19 '78; however, Whitman seems to have been unsure about the precise date of these notes. Whitman seems to have revised this date more than once. In the upper-left-hand corner of the page Whitman indicates that these lines refer to a night in November: "? Later—Nov. Sky." The published version that appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) indicates that these notes describe a time " Early in November ." The Sky—Days and Nights—Happiness was later published in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Down at the Creek [Down at the creek], 1876; ucb.00042; xxx.00821; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 58)
  A prose draft, dated November 8, 1876 and headed "Down at the Creek." Portions of this manuscript appeared under the title November 8, '76 in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). November 8, '76 was later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Mid-day on the beach [Mid-day on the Beach], 1878; ucb.00043; xxx.00822; prose 2 leaves handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 59)
  Various scraps of paper, including two clippings of Whitman's own published prose, pasted together to create two separate leaves. Portions of this manuscript first appeared in Winter Sunshine: A Trip from Canada to the Coast, Philadelphia Times, 26 January 1879. This manuscript contains a nearly complete draft of A Winter Day on the Beach, a section of prose that appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic as How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the heading A Fine Winter Day on the Beach. Whitman dated this draft December 1878, and the manuscript shows evidence of title revisions. A revised version of this prose piece was eventually published as part of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), and finally collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of the second leaf is a portion of a letter from A. B. Ashley to Whitman, requesting an autograph.
- Sea-Shore Fancies [Ever since I have written], 1876–1882; ucb.00044; xxx.00823; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 60)
  A nearly complete draft of Sea-Shore Fancies, a short prose piece that first appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic, as part of How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the section heading A Fine Winter Day on the Beach. Whitman later divided this section into two separate items. The draft represented here was eventually published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), under the title Sea-Shore Fancies, and later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- The first chirping [Feb 11—The first chirping], 1877; ucb.00046; xxx.00824; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 61)
  Notes dated February 10–11, 1877, which read like a series of journal entries. These notes compose a partial draft of Spring Overtures—Recreations, a prose piece which first appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic, as How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the heading Spring Overtures. These notes describing the onset of spring were revised and later published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Spring Overtures—Recreations was finally appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of this manuscript is a partial sketch of a building, with measurements and notes in Whitman's hand.
- Bright is the day [Aug 26—Bright is the day], 1877; ucb.00047; xxx.00825; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 62)
  Notes dated August 26, 1877, describing the "full-starr'd" night sky of late summer. Whitman included revised lines from this manuscript in Full-Starr'd Nights, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Full-Starr'd Nights was eventually collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- A Sun-Bath—Nakedness A Sun-Bath—Nakedness, 1878; ucb.00050; xxx.00826; prose 6 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 65, Folder 66, Folder 67)
  Heavily revised prose notes written on various scraps of paper, including a letter fragment and an envelope addressed to Whitman, some of which have been pasted together to create larger sheets. Together these leaves comprise a nearly complete draft of A Sun-Bath—Nakedness, which Whitman published as part of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Though Whitman dates a portion of these manuscript notes July 18, 1878, this prose piece was published in Specimen Days under the date, August 27, 1877. The verso of the third leaf contains a fragment of a letter to Whitman from an unknown correspondent, whose closing signature has been obscured. This item is catalogued as three separate manuscripts in the Livezey collection; however, as they seem to form a continuous and nearly complete draft, we have grouped them together as one item.
- Warmish today [Feb 10—Warmish to-day], 1877; ucb.00054; xxx.00809; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 68)
  Notes detailing a portion of Whitman's restorative time in the rural area near Timber Creek. These notes first appeared in the 9 April 1881 issue of The Critic as part of How I Get Around at Sixty and Take Notes. (No. 2), under the section heading Convalescent Hours. Whitman further revised these notes before publishing them as a portion of The Oaks and I, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). The Oaks and I was later published in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Though Whitman dated these manuscript notes 10 February 1877, he seems to have been unsure about the precise date of this piece. Published versions of this prose item appeared with a date of 5 September 1877.
- Cloudy and Coolish ['76 White Horse], 1876; ucb.00055; xxx.00811; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 54)
  A Draft fragment of Autumn Side-Bits, that first appeared in the 29 January 1881 issue of The Critic as part of How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes. (No. 1), under the section heading Autumn Scenes and Sights. Whitman further revised this prose piece before including it in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) as part of Autumn Side-Bits, which was later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Another happy day [Sunday Aug 27 '77], 1877; ucb.00048; xxx.00826; 72/234 z 1:64; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 64)
  A heavily revised draft fragment of A Sun-Bath—Nakedness. Much of this manuscript was first published in the 9 April 1881 issue of The Critic under the title How I Get Around at Sixty and Take Notes. (No. 2). Revised portions of this draft were used as the first paragraph of the section titled Convalescent Hours. Whitman further revised these notes before publishing them in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) as A Sun-Bath—Nakedness, which eventually appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of this manuscript is a letter fragment from George G. Clapp to Whitman.
- Birds—And a Caution [May 16, 17], 1881; ucb.00003; xxx.00827; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 54)
  A series of notes, dated 16–17 May 1881. The line which reads "the vocal shuttle of the whip-por-will" appeared nearly verbatim in Birds—And a Caution, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Birds—And a Caution later appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). This manuscript bears similarities in phraseology with Sunday morning, a manuscript held in the Feinberg collection at the Library of Congress, which may be a revised draft of this item.
- Footsteps [Footsteps], 1876–1882; ucb.00009; xxx.00812; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Draft lines and trial titles headed "Footsteps," apparently intended for a preface of some sort. "Footsteps" was possibly a working title for Specimen Days. A single line from this manuscript, "Only the undulations of my Thought beneath under the Night and Stars—or at midday looking out upon the Sea," appeared slightly revised in Final Confessions—Literary Tests, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). Whitman included Final Confessions—Literary Tests in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Nights by a peaceful happy creek [nights by a peaceful happy creek], 1880–1881; ucb.00018; xxx.00834; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 30)
  A heavily revised draft of A Happy Hour's Command, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), which later appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The verso of this manuscript contains two cancelled lines: "In highest Noon I sing & Starry Night" and "with other Pieces & Specimen Days." Though From Noon to Starry Night is an 1881 cluster in Leaves of Grass, there is no other connection between this manuscript and Whitman's published work.
- Specimen days, here and there [good prefatory passage], 1880–1881; ucb.00020; xxx.00834; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Notes intended for a prefatory passage that bear a loose resemblance to ideas and themes presented in A Happy Hour's Command, Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), which later appeared in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). A comment at the top of the page indicates that Whitman considered using these lines in a footnote at the beginning of Specimen Days. Whitman made a similar notation on "I have jotted down these memoranda" (described above), portions of which were used as a footnote to New Themes Entered Upon.
- These notes are all diverted [These notes are all diverted from], 1879–1881; ucb.00023; xxx.00812; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 40)
  A heavily revised draft fragment of Final Confessions—Literary Tests, which first appeared in Specimen Days ( 1882–1883 ), and was later collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of this manuscript is a letter to Whitman from James M. Scovel, dated 7 February 1879.
- Begin a Long Jaunt West Trip to Kansas &c, 1879–1882; ucb.00081; xxx.00956; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Notes with the heading, "Trip to Kansas &c," portions of which Whitman revised and used in Begin a Long Jaunt West, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The verso of this manuscript includes a miscellaneous list, which Whitman identifies as "travelers, merchants, Leadville folk."
- A Meadow Lark [By the Creek], 1878–1882; ucb.00066; xxx.00957; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Notes on the meadow lark, dated 16 March 1878. This manuscript contributed to A Meadow Lark, which first appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), and was collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Clover and Hay Perfume [Hay and corn], 1878–1882; ucb.00067; xxx.00958; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Various scraps of paper pasted together to form three separate leaves. This manuscript is a draft of Clover and Hay Perfume, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and included in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Over the glistening bronze brook [White Butterflies], 1878–1882; ucb.00068; xxx.00959; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Notes on butterflies that Whitman revised and used in Straw-Color'd and Other Psyches, which appeared in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before appearing in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Butterflies (now taking the place) Butterflies, 1877–1882; ucb.00069; xxx.00959; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Two small scraps of paper pasted together to make one leaf. Whitman revised these notes and used them in Straw-Color'd and Other Psyches, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and included in Complete Prose Works ( 1892.